import React, { useEffect, useReducer, useState } from "react";
import Header from "./Components/Header";
import Main from "./Components/Main";
import Loader from "./Components/Loader";
import Error from "./Components/Error";
import StartScreen from "./Components/StartScreen";
import Question from "./Components/Question";
import NextButton from "./Components/NextButton";
import Progress from "./Components/Progress";
import FinishScreen from "./Components/FinishScreen";
import FinishButton from "./Components/FinishButton";
import Footer from "./Components/Footer";
import Timer from "./Components/Timer";
const initialQuestions = [
  {
    question: "Which is the most popular JavaScript framework?",
    options: ["Angular", "React", "Svelte", "Vue"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "Which company invented React?",
    options: ["Google", "Apple", "Netflix", "Facebook"],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "What's the fundamental building block of React apps?",
    options: ["Components", "Blocks", "Elements", "Effects"],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question:
      "What's the name of the syntax we use to describe the UI in React components?",
    options: ["FBJ", "Babel", "JSX", "ES2015"],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "How does data flow naturally in React apps?",
    options: [
      "From parents to children",
      "From children to parents",
      "Both ways",
      "The developers decides",
    ],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "How to pass data into a child component?",
    options: ["State", "Props", "PropTypes", "Parameters"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "When to use derived state?",
    options: [
      "Whenever the state should not trigger a re-render",
      "Whenever the state can be synchronized with an effect",
      "Whenever the state should be accessible to all components",
      "Whenever the state can be computed from another state variable",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "What triggers a UI re-render in React?",
    options: [
      "Running an effect",
      "Passing props",
      "Updating state",
      "Adding event listeners to DOM elements",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 20,
  },
  {
    question: 'When do we directly "touch" the DOM in React?',
    options: [
      "When we need to listen to an event",
      "When we need to change the UI",
      "When we need to add styles",
      "Almost never",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 20,
  },
  {
    question: "In what situation do we use a callback to update state?",
    options: [
      "When updating the state will be slow",
      "When the updated state is very data-intensive",
      "When the state update should happen faster",
      "When the new state depends on the previous state",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question:
      "If we pass a function to useState, when will that function be called?",
    options: [
      "On each re-render",
      "Each time we update the state",
      "Only on the initial render",
      "The first time we update the state",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which hook to use for an API request on the component's initial render?",
    options: ["useState", "useEffect", "useRef", "useReducer"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "Which variables should go into the useEffect dependency array?",
    options: [
      "Usually none",
      "All our state variables",
      "All state and props referenced in the effect",
      "All variables needed for clean up",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "An effect will always run on the initial render.",
    options: [
      "True",
      "It depends on the dependency array",
      "False",
      "In depends on the code in the effect",
    ],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "When will an effect run if it doesn't have a dependency array?",
    options: [
      "Only when the component mounts",
      "Only when the component unmounts",
      "The first time the component re-renders",
      "Each time the component is re-rendered",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 20,
  },
];
const initialState = {
  questions: [],
  status: "loading",
  index: 0,
  answer: null,
  points: 0,
  highscore: 0,
  secondsRemaining: 200,
};
export const reducer = (state, action) => {
  switch (action.type) {
    case "dataReceived":
      return {
        ...state,
        questions: action.payload,
        status: "ready",
      };
    case "dataLoading":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "loading",
      };
    case "dataFailed":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "error",
      };
    case "start":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "active",
      };
    case "finish":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "finished",
        highscore:
          state.points > state.highscore ? state.points : state.highscore,
      };
    case "nextQuestion":
      return {
        ...state,
        index: state.index + 1,
        answer: null,
      };
    case "prevQuestion":
      return {
        ...state,
        index: state.index - 1,
      };
    case "newAnswer":
      const currentQuestion = state.questions.at(state.index);
      return {
        ...state,
        answer: action.payload,
        points:
          action.payload === currentQuestion.correctOption
            ? state.points + currentQuestion.points
            : state.points,
      };
    case "countdown":
      return {
        ...state,
        secondsRemaining: state.secondsRemaining - 1,
        status: state.secondsRemaining === 0 ? "finished" : state.status,
      };
    case "restart":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "active",
        index: 0,
        points: 0,
        answer: null,
        secondsRemaining: 200,
      };

    default:
      throw new Error("Unknown action");
  }
};

const App = () => {
  const [
    { questions, status, index, answer, points, highscore, secondsRemaining },
    dispatch,
  ] = useReducer(reducer, initialState);
  const maximumPoints = questions.reduce((acc, val) => acc + val.points, 0);
  useEffect(() => {
    dispatch({ type: "dataLoading" });
    dispatch({ type: "dataReceived", payload: initialQuestions });
  }, [questions]);
  return (
    <div className="app">
      <Header />
      <Main>
        {status === "loading" && <Loader />}
        {status === "error" && <Error />}
        {status === "ready" && (
          <StartScreen questionsNumber={questions.length} dispatch={dispatch} />
        )}
        {status === "active" && (
          <>
            <Progress
              numQuestions={questions.length}
              index={index}
              points={points}
              maximumPoints={maximumPoints}
              answer={answer}
            />

            <Question
              question={questions.at(index)}
              dispatch={dispatch}
              index={index}
              answer={answer}
            />
            <Footer>
              <Timer dispatch={dispatch} seconds={secondsRemaining} />
              {index + 1 === questions.length ? (
                <FinishButton dispatch={dispatch} />
              ) : (
                <NextButton dispatch={dispatch} answer={answer} />
              )}
            </Footer>
          </>
        )}
        {status === "finished" && (
          <FinishScreen
            points={points}
            maxPossiblePoints={maximumPoints}
            highscore={highscore}
            dispatch={dispatch}
          />
        )}
      </Main>
    </div>
  );
};

export default App;
